Haneul Yoo

Ph.D. STUDENT

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

📞 +82-10-5269-2387 | 🖂 haneul.yoo@kaist.ac.kr | 🍖 haneul-yoo.github.io | 🐧 haneul-yoo | **in** haneulyoo | **y** HaneulYoo13

About ___

Haneul Yoo is a Ph.D. student advised by Alice Oh in the School of Computing at KAIST. Her research interest primarily lies in the intersection of natural language processing and computational social science. In particular, she mainly works on (1) understanding historical documents in low-resource languages and (2) applying and utilizing NLP in language education. She believes there are still myriads of underrepresented languages in NLP, and our efforts on low-resource languages can build more culturally-diverse language models. She also believes language learners can contribute to NLP techniques and data and vice versa.

Education _

KAIST Daejeon, Korea

Ph.D. IN School of Computing Sep 2022 - CURRENT

• Advisor: Alice Oh

KAIST Daejeon, Korea

M.S. IN SCHOOL OF COMPUTING Sep 2022 - Aug 2022

• Advisor: Alice Oh

Ajou University Suwon, Korea

B.S. DOUBLE MAJOR IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING AND DIGITAL MEDIA, GRADUATION WITH HONORS

Mar 2017 - Aug 2020

Sep 2019 - Feb 2020

- University of Wisconsin - Stout, WI, USA — Semester Abroad Winter 2018

Experience ____

LAMDA Lab Suwon, Korea

Research Intern Mar 2020 - Aug 2020

- Study of Deep Learning Model for Bio-signal (EEG) Analysis
- Advisor: Jungryul Seo and Kyung-Ah Sohn

KEPRI Daejeon, Korea

RESEARCH INTERN

- Development of application services utilizing electric used power data
- Advisor: Moonsuk Choi

CSIRO QLD, Australia

RESEARCH INTERN Jul 2019 - Aug 2019

- Convolutional deep neural network for detecting cattle in images/videos
- Advisor: Brano Kusy

Indielist Suwon, Korea

SOFTWARE ENGINEER & CO-FOUNDER

Jul 2018 - Jun 2019

• Establishment of an independent music platform and development of iOS application services

Publications

Rethinking Annotation: Can Language Learners Contribute?

ACL 2023

HANEUL YOO, RIFKI AFINA PUTRI, CHANGYOON LEE, YOUNGIN LEE, SO-YEON AHN, DONGYEOP KANG, AND ALICE OH

Jul 2023

RECIPE: How to Integrate ChatGPT into EFL Writing Education

L@S 2023, Work in Progress

Jieun Han*, **Haneul Yoo***, Yoonsu Kim, Junho Myung, Minsun Kim, Hyunseung Lim, Juho Kim, Tak Yeon Lee, Hwajung Hong, and Alice Oh

Jul 2023

Translating Hanja Historical Documents to Understandable Korean and English

Juhee Son^* , Jiho Jin^* , $\mathsf{Haneul\ Yoo}$, JinYeong Bak, Kyunghyun Cho, and Alice Oh

Dec 2022

EMNLP 2022, Findings

HUE: Pretrained Model and Dataset for Understanding Hanja Documents of Ancient Korea

HANEUL YOO, JIHO JIN, JUHEE SON, JINYEONG BAK, KYUNGHYUN CHO, AND ALICE OH

NAACL 2022, Findings Jul 2022

Knowledge-Enhanced Evidence Retrieval for Counterargument Generation

YOHAN JO, HANEUL YOO, JINYEONG BAK, ALICE OH, CHRIS REED, AND EDUARD HOVY

EMNLP 2021, Findings Nov 2021

Image-based Deep Learning Approach for EEG Signal Classification

HANEUL YOO, JUNGRYUL SEO, AND KYUNG-AH SOHN

KICS Summer Conference 2020

Aug 2020

Proposal and Simulation of Optimal Electric Vehicle Routing Algorithm

MOONSUK CHOI, INJI CHOI, MINHAE JANG, AND HANEUL YOO

KEPCO 2020 Mar 2020

Talks and Teachings _

TA Al Tech Boostcamp (Spring 2023, Fall 2022)

Al Ethics (Spring 2023), Al and Its Social Impact (Spring 2023), KAIST SoC Colloquium (Fall 2021), Machine Learning (Fall 2022, Spring 2021)

Teacher Python at Suwon Information Science High School (Spring 2020), Java at Maetan High School (Spring 2019)

Academic Services

Volunteer FAccT (2022), COLING (2022) **Reviewer** NeurlPS (2021, 2023), EMNLP (2022)

Honors and Awards

KAIST Support Scholarship

KAIST

Jun 2020

Sep 2020 - Current

Graduation with Honors

Outstanding Volunteer Award

Ajou University

SUMMA CUM LAUDE (1ST PLACE)

Aug 2020

Gyeonggi Volunteer Center

Special Prize BIXPO

BIXPO 2019 Nov 2019

Excellence Award KIPA

Creative Start-up Competition Nov 2019

Academic Excellence Scholarship

Asan Foundation

Mar 2017 - Aug 2020

References _____

Alice Oh Professor in School of Computing, KAIST